Hello! Welcome to another Bug Bounty Reports
Explained video! Today, I will show you how
Ryan Pickren found a chain of zero-days that
led to universal cross-site scripting in Safari
which allowed hacking any website. Literally,
any website: Facebook, Gmail, PayPal or your
crypto wallet - whatever... He got a huge bounty
of $100,500 for it. The link to the original, well
well-written blog post, is in the description.
Enjoy! This episode is sponsored by Blaze
Information Security. It's a team of experienced
hackers who specialize in penetration testing
and application security services. They can offer
your company a wide range of services: pentests,
red teams, threat modelling and even the whole
assessment of your remote work infrastructure.
They also have a special package for startups. If
you want to know more, check out blazeinfosec.com.
And I know the owner - he was hacking before
I was even born so he knows his business.
Webarchive files are used to save whole websites:
HTML, CSS, JS and images - everything in a single
file. It's an XML-based format and it looks
like this. The base64 encoded content is here
and here is the origin. Yes, you heard me right
- there is an origin specified. Back in 2013, if
you could control the contents of this file, you
could just put an arbitrary origin, encode the XSS
payload and you would be able to execute the code
on any domain and access any domain's cookies.
Such an attack is called universal XSS. It's not
a bug in a particular website but in the browser
which makes it insanely powerful. The attacker
can steal data from every website that you use
so the potential impact is huge. According
to Google, almost as valuable as an RCE.
So back in 2013, if you could force the victim
into downloading and opening such a file,
you could perform this attack. But it's not how
it works in 2022 with more security mechanisms
in Safari and macOS but let's try to bypass them.
The attack has to start with phishing the victim
into visiting our website. It should not be a
big problem but every single user interaction
makes the attack less and less likely. The first
problem that we encounter from here is prompt
about downloading a file. Because the first
time you download a file from any domain,
Safari will ask you for permission. It would
look quite bad with the attacker domain.
The same goes for opening applications with custom
URL schemes. If you open, let's say a Discord URL,
it will try to use the custom URL scheme.
Safari will then ask you for permission to
open the desktop Discord application. But it's
not for every single URL scheme. There's an
allowlist of trusted Apple applications that
don't have to ask for permission. Among others,
you can use icloud-sharing:// which is opened by
ShareBear application for, as the name suggests,
sharing files over iCloud. It's much helpful
because, apart from being whitelisted by Safari,
it's also a perfect vector for delivering the
webarchive file to the victim - that's great!
But there is a catch. The first time opening
a file, the victim has to confirm it. This is
not an ideal attack scenario but also
not the end of the word. Importantly,
after one confirmation of opening the file,
the attacker can modify the file completely
and the victim won't have to reconfirm
opening it. After the modifications,
ShareBear will automatically download the new
version of the file to the victim's machine.
Ok, so we have delivering the file to the
victim taken care of and now we can run it.
...unless we can't because Gatekeeper
blocks it. Because by default,
any downloaded file on macOS is quarantined.
Gatekeeper prevents executing quarantined files
like shell scripts and webarchives. Yes, they
also thought about webarchives and they explicitly
mentioned them in the documentation.
So when Safari tries to open a file,
it goes through the Gatekeeper and in this case,
webarchives get blocked. We could bypass that
if we would find a vector where Safari opens a
file without asking Gatekeeper. And after a bit of
research, Ryan found out that windows URL files do
exactly that. It's a format that specifies things
like the URL of the shortcut, the icon and so on.
You can just make a desktop shortcut to a website.
You can also use a file:// protocol. And
turns out that if you open this shortcut file,
with a path to webarchive instead of opening the
webarchive directly, it bypasses the Gatekeeper.
And one last piece of the puzzle is the
path of the downloaded webarchive file.
Normally, it will be inside the user directory so
we would need to know the macOS username. It's ok
when you target a specific victim but hard to
predict with an attack on a big scale. To solve
this problem, you can use a DMG file. It's a disk
image format that contains an archive with another
files inside. The reason why it solves the problem
is that it's mounted into /Volumes/ directory
which means we don't need to know the username
to predict its location. So what is it finally?
A webarchive? A DMG? A URL file? I know that you are
confused so let's go through the whole exploit.
First, you have to trick the victim into visiting
your website. This website contains such JavaScriptcode.
It contains a link to a harmless image
shared over iCloud. The user has to confirm the
prompt about opening a file. This is the last
piece of user interaction that we need. Now,
you have to modify the contents of the image to a
DMG file that contains the webarchive inside. In
the real attack scenario, you would probably
need some scripts to do this automatically.
Now Safari launches this file and the disk
image is mounted into /Volumes/ directory.
The webarchive is available under this path.
Now, you modify the contents of the file again.
Importantly, the disk image is already mounted
in /Volumes/ directory and it's not removed
from there or modified even though you make a
modification on your iCloud account. This time,
you turn this file into the URL format,
pointing to the webarchive which is inside
/Volumes/ directory. Inside the webarchive
file, there is your arbitrary JavaScript code
and arbitrary domain which you'd like to attack.
After the webarchive file is launched in Safari,
your code gets executed on whichever domain
you chose. With universal cross-site scripting,
you can do whatever the user can do in their
browser - attack PayPal and transfer funds to you,
attack Gmail and steal or send emails as the
victim. You can attack a website like Zoom or
Facetime which is likely to have permission to the
camera and you can see what the victim is doing.
And many, many more... The reward for this bug
was $100,500 and there were two CVEs issued.
As for the fixes, the ShareBear application
now only reveals a file instead of launching it
directly and WebKit now won't open any quarantined
files, even via Windows shortcuts. If you've
learned anything new from this video, leave a like
and subscribe to the channel. If you want to see
other bug bounty reports from Apple, check out
this playlist on your right. You can find there a
$28,000 IDOR in Apple Shortcuts or $50k RCE. But
for now, thank you for watching and goodbye!